[Music]
so
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
ask widget show today we discuss as you
know
uh current affairs geopolitics history
and all that wonderful stuff so
before we begin let's see who all is
present with us in attendance i can see
rajiv akshay
sampriti sri harsha
bonfire
ravi raj om manish mehul arnab abbay
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you wherever you are
i hope you're all doing very well and
some more sangeeth chaitanya siddharth
great white ajay kumar bunty vijay
shivam mahesh
ruby snow and lots of other people good
evening good day all of you great to
have you all on this show
this evening when there's an india
pakistan cricket match going on so i can
understand if there are of
a little fewer people as than usual but
hey i'm here
so
uh before we begin this
episode is sponsored by abhijit chavda
academy my new course that i've launched
it's a course on indian history in case
you are not aware of it it's the link is
in the description below it's a course
that is still a work in progress i'm
going to cover the entirety of indian
history more or less in that especially
insulin industry so that's a course that
i've launched it's available uh now
the link is in the description i
look forward to seeing you all in there
if you are interested otherwise you can
always watch my channel which has way
more material than the course but the
course is structured in a certain way
and it's chronological so maybe that's
something in case you're interested in
you can acquire
so that's uh the thing now let's get
into the questions let's get into the
questions what questions we have today
and let's go into question number one
question number one is by sahil joshi i
have noticed multiple times that the
ministry of external affairs of india
gives kind of polite and sometimes
assertive statements against any nation
that tries to act against india or
indian interests in some other way gives
me the feeling that some countries are
taking india for granted at the same
time other countries give aggressive
statements even to the slightest issue
do you think india has a very soft and
less aggressive less assertive approach
do you think india should be a little
more assertive in countering such
statements from other nations all right
i would tend to agree with you overall
that the ministry of external affairs of
india is is very uh
it it gives very soft statements very
gentle
non-controversial non-aggressive
non-assertive statements very
conciliatory kind of meek
you know that sort of that's that's the
pattern that you observe overall when it
comes to the ministry of external
affairs of india
for instance in the us in china you have
these daily press briefings of their
ministries of external affairs in the
case of india it's like once a week yeah
so it gets it gives you the feeling that
india is not a major player on the
geopolitical scene you only have once a
week press conferences and very bland
diplomatic you know non-assertive
statements and so on that's what you see
now i have said this in the past let me
say this again diplomacy
is
war by other means
right and the strength of your
diplomatic statements
is a direct reflection of your overall
geopolitical strength your comprehensive
national power
so if you have a nation there is a small
nation with a small economy and a small
military it cannot afford
to be assertive uh diplomatically
the strength of your diplomacy
is directly proportional to your overall
strength the larger the stick the hard
power you hold the more assertive your
diplomacy can be american diplomats are
very brash they are sometimes very
un-diplomatic
it's because the us is a global geomet
geopolitical hegemon it's the only
superpower the chinese are now aspiring
to be a superpower since then this
instant 2012 they have changed their
approach they are now indulging in what
they what is called a wolf warrior
diplomacy very aggressive very assertive
diplomacy very brash statements very
harsh statements right
and india is not there yet
india is still 3 something trillion
dollar economy we are not even a five
trillion dollar economy as your economy
grows your military strengths grow
strength grows once you reach a certain
stage you can afford
to speak in a different way
diplomatically so this style of your
diplomacy is a direct reflection of your
overall standing in the geopolitical
chess board right
so yes i agree that
that the diplomacy that india does is
kind of kind of a little bit submissive
kind of meek that's what the chinese did
for the longest time they swallowed all
the insults that the western nations
heaped upon them chinese diplomats
before 2012 were always conciliatory
meek
humble
non-confrontational
non-assertive non-aggressive they had
this policy for the longest time they
swallowed all the insults it's only
after 2012 that they changed their
approach
then shopping said uh hide your
strengths and bide your time right he
said that in the late 20th century and
that's what the chinese followed for the
longest time india also needs to follow
this approach there's no point making
very strong diplomatic statements if you
cannot back them up with actual facts on
the ground with actual military strength
right now let me also point something
out i mean recently there has been some
some interesting
diplomacy from india which is something
that's not that i've not seen before let
me put that on the screen so recently
the chinese
ambassador in sri lanka made some
ridiculous statements about india that
india has
been aggressive against sri lanka like
17 india has visited aggression on sri
lanka 17 times that sort of thing
without naming india but he referred to
the northern neighbor which is only
india right so he made some very uh
in judicious and false statements about
india and this was the response this
came in yesterday from indian from the
indian
uh diplomatic mission in sri lanka it
says we have noted the remarks of the
chinese ambassador his violation of
basic diplomatic etiquette may be a
personal trait or reflecting of a larger
national attitude
how
sarcastic and scathing that is
his view of the sri lanka of sri lanka's
northern neighbor may be colored by
how his own country behaves
india we assure him is very different
he's imputing a geopolitical context to
the visit of a purported scientific
research vessel is a giveaway opaqueness
and depth debt-driven agendas are now a
major challenge especially for smaller
nations recent developments are a
caution sri lanka needs support not
unwanted pressure or unnecessary
controversies to serve another country's
agenda this is i believe the harshest
diplomatic statement i've ever seen in
india issue
in my entire i mean
my living memory i have never seen india
issue such a strong and harsh and
scathing diplomatic statement
i mean it is still a classy statement
it's not it's not vulgar and impolite
but it's scathing
right and it it uh
makes things very clear that the chinese
are lying and the chinese have put
srilanka into the debt trap which they
do to other nations
and yeah and the entire
the the entire matter of the chinese pie
ship that came to sri lanka that docked
there it obviously has geopolitical
context and all that so this is i
believe a break from india's tradition
i've never seen such a strong and harsh
diplomatic statement from india now some
very intelligent people are telling me
on twitter that india should have sunk
the chinese vessel very quietly uh those
people need they have a lot of growing
up to do i would say yeah sinking or a
major
research vessel or spy ship quietly i
mean what are you people smoking so yeah
so anyway that's a different matter
so my point is this
we are seeing slightly more assertive
diplomacy from india it's something that
can only be
a reflection of india's overall
geopolitical strength and standing
diplomacy is a direct reflection of your
hard power
right and india still
isn't a major major uh power in asia
india is the only nation that can stand
up to china and we are showing it from
time to time but india has a long way to
go before india can change its
diplomatic approach right india needs to
become i would say a 10 trillion dollar
economy before india can change its
diplomatic approach five trillion
dollars is the first milestone we have
to reach and then 10 billion dollars
when you reach that status 10 trillion
trillion dollars then the chinese will
realize that there is nothing they can
do about india india is it is what it is
if you are a three trillion dollar
economy and there are 15 trillion dollar
economy nearly then they can
uh
believe that they can ride a rough shot
over you right so india the only thing
india needs to do is to put our we have
to put our head down and work as hard as
possible for the next 10 20 years
only then will you see a change in
india's diplomatic approach right
so yeah so that's what i have to say
about this
samartha gandhi says dr s joshenkar
recently visited our argentina and his
visit has improved the relations between
to a great extent
any impact on india uk free trade pact
in india uk ties considering india's
position on this issue
right so it's interesting that the
indian visit
the indian external defense minister's
visit to argentina is being linked to
india uk relations now why is it so why
is uh samar
speaking about that so let's explain why
it is so right there's always
more that means i when it comes to
geopolitics especially argentina so
let's go to the map
and understand
why
this is something that has to do with
argentina and in the uk so argentina is
this nation here
right the big nation at this uh the
southern extremity of the
uh south american continent
so this all has to do with the falkland
islands
which are which the argentines called
las islas malvinas the malvinas islands
the british call them the falkland
islands now these islands are obviously
off the coast of argentina so one would
expect that they would belong to
argentina but no they belong
to this nation up here the united
kingdom
and the argentines have always claimed
this this uh
archipelago so in the 1980s early 1980s
argentina tried to acquire this uh
piece of maritime real estate by force
margaret thatcher the then prime
minister of the uk sent an expeditionary
force the naval force to fight the
argentines there was a brief falklands
war and the british won right and
obviously the british were supported by
various other larger geopolitical powers
and so on as you know
so the british control
this archipelago
and this is a disputed territory the
argentine government and the argentina
nation has always
repeatedly said that it belongs to them
now this is this is something that will
be resolved in due course of time so
this is a dispute a territorial dispute
between the uk argentina
india
now has excellent relations with the
argentines it's it's a work in pro
progress obviously but dr joshua visited
argentina very recently and things are
looking good
when it comes to india
argentina relations right and the
interesting matter is this let me put
something else on the screen
so there was a joint statement between
india
and argentina
let me show you the joint statement
let's put that on the screen
india reiterated its support to the
resumption of negotiations to find a
solution to the sovereignty issue
relating to the question of the malvinas
islands in accordance with the
resolutions of the united nations
general assembly and the special
committee on decolonization
so this is this should be a
non-controversial statement etc the only
thing that raises a little bit of
eyebrows is
the nomenclature
so
india has chosen to call these islands
the malvinas islands not the falklands
islands so it is an implicit recognition
of the validity of argentina's claim on
the islands by using the name that the
argentines use for the islands instead
of using the name the british use for
the islands it's like if you
there is a different dispute between
china and japan about the senkaku
islands which
the chinese called the diyu islands so
if india were to refer to the islands as
the senkaku
as the senkaku islands then it means
that india is implicitly supporting the
japanese claim but if india were to call
the islands the diyu islands it would
mean that india has implicitly supported
the chinese claim of the islands that's
just a hypothetical scenario i'm
offering you to understand
how these things work so india in this
joint statement referred to the islands
as the malvinas islands
which is implicitly supporting the
argentine claims you could construe it
in that matter but india is indirectly
and implicitly giving a little bit of
support to argentina's claims on a claim
on the
island uh archipelago right and why not
the british have always had a history of
supporting
all kinds of anti-india activities
there's a lot of anti-india
activities that go on on british
territory on british soil
lots of pakistani supporters are
are on british territory other kinds of
supporters also separate
separatists who want to see india
fragmented all of that is being
supported and fomented on british
territory the british have always
supported pakistan in their terroristic
activities and other activities against
india they created pakistan they broke
india into pieces so why should india
not pay them back a little bit right
right now india is still a smaller
smallish nation when it comes to overall
geopolitical power yeah
but yes india is a growing nation and
this is going to germinate into a bigger
bigger tree in the future and they
deserve it
right so yeah
there is
an implicit support to the argentinian
claim on the malvinas islands
and not the british claim on that uh on
that island archipelago now will this
impact india uk whatever ties etc who
cares the uk
is more or less a non-entity now the
only relevance the uk it's still one of
the major economies here
india has recently surpassed the uk
overall gdp recently
so uh the uk is still
a major uh
financial hub the only relevance the uk
has globally let me assure you the only
relevance the united kingdom has
globally is as the global center of
money laundering
london is the epicenter of global money
laundering
all these various shell companies that
you can create in the uk if you have
sufficient money you can do anything you
want yeah
and all the fugitives of the world like
to have a house in london or somewhere
in the uk so the only real relevance
that the earthquake british empire has
is as a puppet of the us and the global
money laundering hub all the various
dodgy arms dealers of the of the middle
east all the various saudi shakes and
princes all the various dictators and
despots of the world in various puppet
dictators in africa in other places they
all have investments in the uk they all
have bungalows or or flats penthouse
flats in london
so that's the only relevance the uk has
now whether it affects the india uk
trade pact and all that doesn't really
matter india is going to anyway surpass
all these irrelevant nations and it is
in their interests to have good good
relations with india because it will
help them financially india is a growing
power india is a growing economy no
one's going to stop india from from
achieving what it wants to achieve the
next 20 years india will most likely
surpass the 10 trillion dollar mark
unless there is something that is like a
global catastrophe which i don't see
hopefully happening so it is in the uk's
interest
to get in line and have good relations
with india if they don't want it they
can go to hell and take a hike that's
all that matters yeah so yeah that's
what i can say about this matter
ananda biswas says recently
uh so called putin's brain alexander
dugan there was an assassination attempt
on him unfortunately his daughter fell
prey to that what's your take on this
incident and who do you think must be
behind this attack ukraine u.s et cetera
in the future can such incidents
escalate to major steps taken by russia
so who is alexander dugan he is a
historian philosopher writer
that sort of person he's a scholar he's
an intellectual
he
has authored books on various topics
including on geopolitics one of the only
books on geopolitics that makes sense in
my opinion yeah
yeah so he is
intellectual he's not a politician he's
not a powerful person you may have a
great following it doesn't mean you are
powerful yeah so he is an influential
person he's a very uh
significant scholar writer historian
geopolitical analyst
and so on
but he's not a powerful politician or
any such thing
some people allege that he is the
brain behind putin not so i i don't
agree with that putin is his own man he
doesn't need the blessings or or the
inputs from somebody to to do what he's
doing right
so i disagree that uh uh uh alexander
dugan is putin's brain and the and the
the brain behind
russia's geopolitical geostrategic
initiatives and all that right now the
thing is this yes there was an
assassination attempt on him uh he was
supposed to get into a car there was a
bomb in that car unfortunately what
happened is that he at the last minute
went to another car and his daughter
went into the car that had a bomb and
the car blew up and his daughter
unfortunately died his daughter was a
reasonably young person late twenties
early thirties daria dugina yeah
i think she was a journalist or
something so yes
the bomb wasn't
intended for alexander dugan it ended up
killing his daughter you see geopolitics
is not child's play it's deadly serious
people this is what happens
yeah it is not child's play it is it is
a very grown-up matter it's a matter of
life and death people die and this is
what happened right so this is clearly
an act of terrorism
you
when somebody whoever did this
well they targeted unarmed civilians
non-combatants right when you are
targeting people who are not fighters
people who are not soldiers people who
are not part of the military when you're
targeting civilians that is terrorism
so whoever has done this has indulged in
a blatant act of terrorism now the
western media will justify they will say
that he was evil and his daughter was
part of the regime and blah blah blah so
it's perfectly justifiable to kill them
the western media
is known to portray outright terrorists
as austere religious scholars and so on
so forth they will justify anything any
kind of bloodshed any kind of barbarism
to uh
you know in in service of the of the
empire that's what they will do that's
what the western media is known to do
they will whitewash the worst of crimes
as long as those crimes are in the
service of their cause
so uh the truth is what happened is an
act of terrorism yeah so what's my take
on this incident who is behind this well
i don't have any actual information one
can surmise that maybe it's the
ukrainians who are behind this now we
know who is
who is the perpetrator of ukraine's the
u.s right but the americans will never
get their own hands dirty in this they
will never get involved in such
acts of terrorism directly they will if
they do it
we know that they have done this done
things like this in the past
yeah
look at the history of the past 50 60
years they the americans have been all
behind all kinds of regime change
operations and the coups kudatas and
various dictatorships dictators
see that track record in in south
america it's it's terrible so it would
not be surprising if overall maybe there
is some us hand in that but they will
definitely not be involved directly in
this
they will be involved via proxy if at
all the proxy is obviously i would
expect somebody in ukraine or maybe the
ukraine government or some portion of
the u.s ukrainian military or something
like that
right
so the blame or the suspicion will
obviously go towards ukraine
now uh can such incidents in the future
escalate to something major
the intention would be that
see when you target somebody who is a
civilian
but who is considered who's very well
respected and may be admired and maybe
loved in his nation
and when it ends up killing his daughter
well the intention is to
put the leadership of russia in a very
tight position
that they have to respond to this
right so the intention whether whether
it was alexander
who was killed or whether his daughter
was killed the intention was to provoke
vladimir putin and put him in a
difficult position that he has to
respond in order to placate the people
who feel that
these people killed our scholar and you
did nothing about it
and therefore
by doing that by putting mr putin in
such a difficult position you may induce
him to make some kind of mistake and
some miscalculation so the ukraine war
is proceeding in in a slow war format
right old-fashioned 20th century warfare
no
uh it's it's not bits creek warfare it's
a very slow and steady war that's going
on right
so maybe that's not what the west wants
that's what not what the ukrainians and
the americans want maybe they want mr
putin to make some some some harsh and
silly and stupid decision that will end
up costing him some
costing him
so
overall
i would expect that the intention behind
this terrorist act was to put pressure
on mr putin and induce him into making
some kind of mistake that he would
otherwise not have made and thus far we
are seeing that it's been a few days
since this incident happened there has
been no actual response from the
russians
right so sometimes if you want
if you want to win a war
you have to sometimes swallow some
provocations
and not respond to provocations designed
to induce you into making a mistake so
we have seen no response essentially
from the russians maybe they will
eventually respond at a time and place
of their choosing
right but there has been no knee-jerk
response from the russian government
from vladimir putin for from any any
such quarters so if the the intention
was to provoke the russian government
into making some
some miscalculation of some mistake that
has not worked right so there we are
pierce says what are your views on india
purchasing u.s drones worth three
billion dollars is it a bit expensive if
so what
what should have been done of those
three billion dollars instead of
purchasing drones
we do need drones so these drones that
are being referred to here are those
reaper drones i believe mq-9 reaper or
something i think that's what it's
called now these drones are high
altitude high endurance drones and these
are hunter killer drones so they are not
only used for surveillance they carry a
massive significant not very massive
period but a significant payload
um they can carry bombs missiles various
things they can be used for
surveillance in the maritime domain
oversea yeah they can be used to take
out various targets at sea they can be
used in mountainous terrain they can be
used
uh high above the india let's say india
china border look deep into chinese
chinese occupied territory and maybe if
required
you know take some action that sort of
thing the americans have in the past use
these drones for
anti-terrorism operations in pakistan
and afghanistan
yeah
and the british operate some some of
these drones i think even the french may
have some of them and so on so forth so
this is a very well proven system it's
obviously very expensive yes i uh 30
drones for three billion dollars a
hundred million dollars per piece that's
a tad expensive one would
say
but india does need these drones i would
say that
maybe this purchase is a stop gap
purchase we need a few drones right now
let's acquire these drones use them for
now use them for the next 10 years or so
in the meanwhile develop our own drone
technology i don't think it's very
difficult to develop your own
our own indigenous drone technology we
already have some rustam or some drone
you know medium altitude
uh
kind of uh drone yeah so we are doing
that we have acquired israeli heron
drones
uh i think india needs to invest
significant amounts of uh resources into
developing our own
versions of these high altitude medium
altitude and long endurance drones right
what's a long endurance drone typically
a drone that can loiter and stay in the
air for 10 hours plus more than 10 hours
with a significantly good payload and
there are two for two varieties medium
altitude and high altitude
so medium altitude would be less than 10
kilometers i would say maybe five or so
kilometers up in the air and high high
altitude is 10 plus 10 to 15 kilometers
up in the air that sort of thing so the
mq-9 reaper drone is a high high
altitude long endurance drone
so i would imagine that india does need
these drones they are expensive yes or
anything you purchase from the americans
is going to be expensive it's going to
cost you money yeah
so i think it's a stop gap arrangement
the turks have developed their own
drones
i forget the name it's a turkish name
good good drones yeah uh even the
iranians are developing those the
chinese have their own drones so india
should get into this thing and india
should also develop its own drone
technology
for a family of various kinds of drones
medium altitude high altitude and long
endurance that sort of thing hunter
killer drones surveillance drones
whatever we need to do that get
your act together hal drdo whoever is
involved in this needs to happen so yes
uh it is something that most likely
india needs right now uh until we have
our own
indigenously designed and developed
drones we would need to acquire a few
drones as a stop gap measure as a
temporary measure and to keep uncles
unhappy that you know we are acquired we
are buying your weapons
so there's also a geopolitical and
diplomatic uh most likely angle to this
to tell the americans that you know we
are not buying everything from the
russians we are also buying your weapons
and we are spending some money on that
so it it uh serves multiple purposes
so yeah i think it's a necessary evil
get some drones from from the americans
they are good drones i'm sure they're
well proven they do work they're
effective so get these drones i i don't
think it's finalized yet but it's in the
final stages of approval or whatever
it's called this entire deal
so maybe by the end of this year the
next four five months we will uh the inc
it will be the the signature should be
done and
soon enough india would be able to
acquire those 30
pieces of aerial hardware
the long-term game is to develop our own
drone technology and become
self-sufficient
in all these military uh hardware and
software matters
udid says is the western media's
obsession about finnish prime minister
sanna marin's party video a destruction
from what's happening in ukraine in
taiwan
oh yes this poor lady so what happened
so the swede the finnish prime minister
her name is sana marin she is a
she's a reasonably young person i think
she's in her mid-30s 35 36 years old and
uh recently
this all came out in social in the
social media that she was
filmed partying with various other
people and it looks bad so let's let's
take a look at the images
sana marin
party
let's put that on the screen i i feel i
feel sorry for her
i mean
is there is there any rule that
if you're a prime minister you cannot
have a party once in a while so yeah
this is what's emerged
i
i don't think there's anything wrong in
having a party once in a while with your
friends or whatever yeah it looks a
little it makes you look a little bit
immature and
non-leader-like i mean the americans
in the 2020 elections
one of the main things the democrats one
of the main uh
criticisms the democrats had about
president trump
was that he was unpresidential he was
not leader-like he did not have the the
the gravitas that a president would have
he was a little bit funny and you know
he did not behave like a president so
the same allegation can be made uh
about this lady that the video that was
leaked out it makes her appear unprime
ministerial
it makes her look like a regular person
not somebody who's a prime minister and
the leader of a nation
so uh so that's what it is the the
so how do we
uh
how do we judge the performance of a
leader
is it is it important
if they have a party once in a while in
their personal life after hours
is there anything wrong with that
i don't understand why there is
something wrong with that i'm sure she
works every single day
i'm sure she's not missed a single day
of work ever since she became prime
minister
and everybody has their own way of
winding down maybe she likes to party
with some friends i don't see anything
wrong with that yeah it makes her look
silly so this is clearly a political
ploy by somebody who video who
videotaped this and then leaked this the
the film
to the media and social media and all
that yeah it's clearly uh what's called
a hatchet job somebody is stabbed in the
back it's it's a political ploy
obviously
so uh
so issue to blame for what happened i
think you should have been a little more
discreet it's okay to party but don't
make sure that it doesn't get leaked out
right
everybody needs to wind down no matter
how hard you work no matter how serious
you are as a leader of your nation once
in a while you need to indulge in some
sort of
behavior that distracts you for some
time from the pressures of your work
some people like to sleep some people
like to read some people like to
meditate some people like to party this
lady likes to party i see nothing wrong
with that
so
clearly somebody has
done a hatchet job on her i feel sorry
for her i don't know how what her
politics is whether she's good or bad as
a leader i have absolutely no idea
finland is not a very significant nation
as far as i'm concerned so i have not
ever really followed finnish politics i
know that overall
a position in the geopolitical chess
board you know of finland has always
been the the frontier nation against the
russians they had a war with the
russians did in the 1930s and the 40s
some somewhere around there yeah and
right now they're trying to apply to
become a member of nato and they've
always been very of the russians they
have a very strong civilian recruitment
program in which civilians have dual
roles like they serve in the military
everybody has
those who are part of that have weapons
and they are available at very short
notice to join the armed forces and all
that
so uh that's the situation about finland
i i kind of feel sorry for her this lady
but she should have i in my opinion she
should have been a little more careful
about who she allows
to film her
so yeah that's what happens uh i'm sure
it's a lesson she'll never forget
uh will it affect her standing as prime
minister maybe maybe not yeah that's how
it goes
so yeah is it a distraction from what's
happening in ukraine and taiwan
maybe maybe that's also one of the
purposes for having this controversy
erupt people like controversies people
like it when some leader is caught doing
something that is not very leader like
you know it's it's uh
it's it's great material for the gossip
mills
and
the media loves it the media loves the
sort of thing so yeah it's a it's a good
distraction if there was a purpose
to distract the people from what's
happening in ukraine taiwan taiwan
obviously the chinese are tightening the
screws they're tightening the screws in
taiwan they are now no longer
recognizing the taiwanese airspace and
their maritime waters and all that they
are they are sending drones over or
taiwan or the island of taiwan you know
the chinese
and so on so taiwan's sovereignty is
under a big cloud a big dark cloud
the chinese are slowly tightening the
screws they are putting the taiwanese
people under the siege kind of mentality
illusion right
and that's what's happening that's not
very good for taiwan and taiwan is
obviously um well
it's it's one of the what what you would
call the u.s massive states
uh when it comes to ukraine things are
not going when the nuclear the western
media and all the various disposable
minions on social media you know they
will
portray the taiwan
sorry the ukraine war as a lost cause
for russia but hey look at the maps look
at the situation in the ground inch by
inch meter by meter the russians are
advancing they're consolidating their
positions and they're gonna get what
they want
and there's nothing the americans can do
about it in the long run ukraine
unfortunately whether we like it or not
may have had its borders redrawn
permanently so things are not going well
in ukraine things are not going very
well in taiwan still taiwan is still
secure for now
of course that's coming into the cloud
so things are not going very well for
american interests in ukraine in taiwan
so yeah maybe people do need a
destruction from time to time uh there
could be more distractions coming in in
the future who knows
new things coming up in the air
masks again who knows who knows they'll
come up with anything
so yeah that's where we are right now
tomislav nagi says i am a european i
have never in my whole life created any
human being badly because of ethnicity
race or language to say that every
european is racist is not acceptable
i agree
it's not acceptable to say that every
european is racist are you saying that i
have said that i don't think i have ever
said that every european is racist if
it sounded like i may have meant it that
way then i will readily apologize i do
not believe that every european is
racist there are lots of good people in
europe i know that for a fact not every
european is racist
but let's look at it from a different
perspective every single european nation
or kingdom or empire that has
participated in colonization has used
racism to justify its policies and it's
its actions that is indeed a truth
indeed the truth
it's always
boiled down to civilizing the backward
natives
they are savages they need to be
civilized so that's always been the
pretext
to justify
the actual actions that they are
perpetrated which is genocide in
colonization and plunder and loot and
destruction of entire nations and
civilizations and cultures
so that has indeed been the truth now
let's say belgium did horrific
atrocities in africa and it was all
racism they used racist racist
um
arguments
to justify what they did it doesn't mean
that every single person who lived in
belgium at the time was racist there
would have been lots of good people in
belgium who had no not an ounce of
racism in them
yes
so
it is completely unacceptable to say
that every european is racist completely
unacceptable i completely agree with you
but overall the history of europe
especially in the past 500 years the the
age of colonialism has been an age of
unbridled racism
so you may not be a racist i'm not sure
what nation you're from nagi means
hungary i'm sure hungary uh
i don't think hungary has as far as i
can recall indulged in colonial
activities
and the people of hungary are very nice
people as far as i know whatever
experience whatever little experience
i've had so i totally agree with you to
say that every europe in this races is
completely unacceptable that itself is
racism to say that all europeans are
racist
so yeah
the world is complicated it's complex
history
i mean if you look at the overall
history of europe overall it's it's not
a very bad very very good history in the
past 500 years even if you look at the
history of the past 1000 plus years i
mean the destruction of european culture
the original native indo-european
culture is a tale of horrific
atrocities and sorrow sorrows the
northern crusades and also
europe has
a
very very dark history unfortunately if
you look at
the past 500 past 1000 or 1500 years
and even if you look at the
various other things that happen in
europe the
um the expansion of the anglo-saxons
into the uk
what's now the uk the british islands
that itself was bloody brutal there was
a lot of racism there the irish were
looked upon as as second-class citizens
the celtic peoples
they endured an enormous amount of
racism from the anglo-saxons
i'm sure people don't know this at all
the irish were treated like second-class
sub-human citizens
by the by the english speakers the irish
and all the other celtic peoples of the
british islands whether it is the welsh
whether it is the scots or the irish
yeah so there's been a lot of this the
roman
history itself is nothing to i mean it's
portrayed as glorious by european
historians but hey hey
they create a wasteland and they call it
peace
that's what the romans used to do it's
not my quote look it up
so overall the history of the human
species is a history of warfare it's a
history of violence we are inherently
violent
yeah but i totally agree with you this
love nagi that to say that every
european is racist is absolutely
unacceptable there are lots of good
people in europe even today even in the
past even during the time when europe
was destroying the the rest of the
civilized world even then you would have
had good people in europe but overall
yeah we know what the history is
okay lecture says in your experience are
there any countries in europe that are
culturally similar to bharat india
and is it ever possible for indians to
be friends with europeans in spite of
racism and hindu phobia look
it is of course possible for indians to
be friends with europeans there are lots
of good people in every nation in the
world in every culture in the world no
matter which part of the geography of
the planet you go to you will find lots
of good people there
right so yeah there is racism in europe
but not all europeans are racist there
is hindu phobia in the entire western
world that originates in certain things
but not everyone is a hindu foreign
right
it is certainly possible for indians to
be friends with europeans not all
europeans but many europeans i'm sure
now is there any nation in europe that
is culturally similar to bharat in the
past the whole of europe
had its own
native
culture and civilization the old
indo-european culture
so the old european indo-european
culture was the same as the old
indian culture
which to some extent still exists in
india right hinduism
indo-european culture was nothing but
that in its in its all different kinds
of local manifestations
the roman gods are the same as the
indian gods the greek gods are the
ancestors of the roman gods the romans
adopted the greek gods the greek gods
are the same as the indian gods the
persian gods are the same as the indian
gods the indian gods are the oldest of
the gods right the same pantheon you
will see it in the nordic pantheon thor
is indra thor is the thunder god and the
hammer god that's what indra is thor
defeats this great sea serpent
what did indra do he defeated the great
serpent vritra who swallowed the oceans
of the world and so on so forth so the
same culture existed all across europe
it was destroyed
by the abrahamic culture it was
destroyed uprooted through horrific
barbaric means this is the truth look at
the history of europe study it
today's historians won't
highlight those matters
but pick up history textbooks
pick up any good history textbook that
deals with the history of europe in the
past 2000 years they will
focus on that briefly but it's there
we know what happened the entire
indigenous culture of europe was
destroyed so below the surface in europe
we still have elements of the old
culture let me give you a couple of
examples here
so the religion is now the abrahamic
religion as we know yes but there is
still elements of
european culture old european culture
but still left behind
here's an example from lithuania do we
know where lithuania is look it up on
the map i will show you an example of
lithuanian culture
so traditional lithuanian houses are
adorned with the motif of two horse
heads the ashwins the baltic
counterparts of the rig vedic ashwin the
divine horse twins old lithuanian ashwa
and sanskrit ashwa mean the same thing
horse take a look at this
traditional lithuanian house if it will
ever load here it is
as you can see there's a there's this
motif of
twin horses on top of it
here is
a better image of that
so this is one example
of old european culture there which is
very similar
to indian culture which which
essentially originated indian culture
here's something else
let's take a look at the linguistics
words in english sanskrit and lithuanian
you is dwam in sanskrit which is two in
lithuanian
who is kash in sanskrit which is kash in
when
in english is kada in sanskrit how do i
say in sanskrit when will i be happy you
say kadasukhi bhavamiyam
so kada
is kada in lithuanian sheep aves
horse ashwa ashwa go iti
[Music]
so if you look at the lithuanian
language it sounds just like sanskrit
the pronunciations will be different
different today
nobody in lithuania will remember the
origin of that language but here we are
you see it right in front of you so
there is so much even today that is in
that the european culture has in common
with india especially when you when you
uh
go slightly below the surface and at the
surface you will see the abrahamic
culture and that is still very strong in
various parts of europe but if you go a
few layers beneath the surface you will
see the true indo-european culture which
still exists
at sub-surface levels and all that yeah
so there's plenty in common between
india and europe
to a certain extent
okay pramod singh says please light your
thoughts on the missing nuclear device
on the nanda devi does it still exist
interesting interesting where is this
let's take a look
at the map
let's uh
put the map on the screen let's find
this
mountain nanda devi so i think nanda
devi is the second tallest mountain peak
in india the tallest one is kanchanjanga
and nanda devi is somewhere in
northern india in the himalayan region
in the
near rishikesh
okay let's just search for it it's
somewhere in this region
and here we go here it
is so this is the mountain peak
nanda devi
you can see it on the satellite image
which will not make a lot of sense
over here but there it is this is the
mountain peak the second highest
mountain peak in india
right so what happened here
so as you can see it is very close to
chinese occupied tibet
yes
so what's the story behind this missing
nuclear device
so what happened is this okay so this is
something that happened in 1965.
so let us put this
into okay let me just put keep that on
the on the screen the map so that you
understand what's happening
so
what happened in 1965 to put things in
context
uh the the the magnificent prime
minister of into the greatest prime
minister ever mr nehru very sadly and
regrettably died in 1964.
mr nehru died in may 1964
and mr shastri became prime minister of
india mr shastri as we know died in
january 1966.
so this happened this entire matter
happened in 1965 when mr shastri was the
prime minister of india so the chinese
had
uh tested a nuclear weapon for the first
time in 1964.
in chinese occupied
territory xinjiang so-called xinjiang
etc
so what the americans
the americans were obviously concerned
about this
so they wanted to
spy on chinese uh military activities
nuclear activities in chinese occupied
tibet xinjiang that region
and uh
so they entered into some kind of
agreement with the government of india
that they would place
an observing a monitoring station some
monitoring devices etc
on top of the nanda devi mountain
at the summit of the mountain in india
and the nandavi mountain is nearly eight
kilometers almost eight kilometers tall
slightly less than eight kilometers so
from there you could see deep into
chinese occupied territory maybe 50
kilometers away where this entire thing
was happening right so what happened is
that in 1965 a team of indian and
american mountaineers
climbed up
the nanda devi
mountain what were they carrying they
were carrying a surveillance equipment
so there was an antenna or two antennas
and there were nuclear powered devices
plutonium powered radio isotope
thermoelectric generators
okay so i think there were seven
plutonium capsules and the
thermoelectric generator
and some surveillance equipment that
would be powered
by the the radioactive radioisotope
thermoelectric generator
so this attempt to scale the mountain
was done by a team of 14 american
mountaineers i think and a bunch of
indian mountaineers too because the
indians also had to be involved this is
indian territory we need to see what
they're doing
this was attempted sometime in 1965 the
attempt
failed they tried to climb the mountain
and while they were climbing the
mountain they were high up i believe
some place and there was a blizzard a
massive storm
and they had no option but to go back
down otherwise they would have frozen to
death
and the storm was so severe they had to
leave the equipment on the mountain
so they left the equipment the
radio isotope thermoelectric generators
the plutonium capsules etc they left it
on a ledge or platform somewhere on the
mountain and they went down and they
were able to make it down alive they
they did not lose any lives right so
this happened in 1965
the next year in the spring of 1966
after the death death of mr shastri
the same american climbers returned to
the mountain they climbed it up again
and they knew where they had kept the
equipment
and what they found in the spring
of 1966 is that the equipment was
missing so they surmised
that there were there must have been an
avalanche
you know
on the mountain which swept away all the
equipment this happens
uh in the himalayas avalanches are
common in the on the mountain also
avalanches are reasonably common so they
surmised that there was an avalanche
while they were not there and all the
equipment
was swept down somewhere downhill
because of this avalanche then there was
another attempt in 1967 which is said to
have been a partial success i have no
idea what that means and then there was
a third attempt again in 1967 on a
different mountain this time it was on
the nanda coat mountain
so nanda devi is here where is on the
court it's here
if you can see there is a different
mountain called nanda coat it is a it is
a slightly
smaller mountain not as high as nanda
devi so the third attempt which they did
on this smaller mountain was a success
they were able to put the equipment
there and it worked and they were able
to monitor whatever the chinese were
doing right so all of this happened in
the 1960s it was all secret
in 1978 the indian prime minister muraja
revealed everything this is what the
americans did he was very strongly
anti-us np whatever yeah
so that's what happened that's how the
story came in out into the public domain
because mr murady they say revealed
what had happened what had transpired in
the 1960s now
some people say that because of this so
so the question is first of all what
happened to the missing equipment the
equipment that was placed on a ledge or
a platform
or some flat surface on the mountain in
1965 when they came back the next year
it had disappeared
so the official story is that there was
an avalanche which would have swept it
down and maybe it's lying somewhere
frozen in the frozen
in the ice and the snow of the mountain
somewhere downhill and it's such a big
mountain it's very hard to
to find the equipment
so one interpretation or one uh scenario
is that the equipment was lost in an
avalanche it was swept down downhill and
it's still lying somewhere there the
second
plausible scenario is that the indian
government
later on symptoms sent some climbers
quietly and retrieved the equipment for
research analysis or whatever so that's
the two possibilities either the indian
government acquired the
equipment
secretly or the equipment was actually
lost what if the equipment was lost and
it's still lying somewhere there is it a
problem
well let's understand what plutonium is
plutonium is the thing is the element
that is in the radio isotope
thermoelectric generator that was
supposed to power the the the devices
the surveillance equipment
so plutonium
is a radioactive element
plutonium-238 is what was used in the
radioactive isotope it has a half-life
of 88 years which means in 88 years time
half of the plutonium will have decayed
so it is the heat source in the
thermoelectric generators the actual
more common plutonium is plutonium-239
which is the primary fissile isotope in
nuclear weapons it has a half-life of 24
000 years that is gonna last forever
essentially and then there is protein in
plutonium-214 241 also so the plutonium
we are talking about that we are
concerned about is the plutonium-238
that was present in those capsules and
in the devices now in case it is still
lying around
on the mountain
you know somewhere in the foothills of
the mountain
the thing is this this region
is the catchment area
from where
the ganga gets its waters
there are there are these big mountain
peaks here these are the himalayas there
are glaciers that over time slowly melt
and then there are these major rivers
here the alakananda the bhagirathi that
feed the river ganga
this all happens in
not rishikesh but deva prayag i think
it's in deva prayer that the
in
meet together
here it is
so you have one river which is the
alakananda
the other one is the bhagirathi they get
together here and then they are called
the ganga so it is in devaprayag that
the ganga river actually takes shape
and then it comes downwards
into rishikesh and then down towards the
down towards mainland india and so on so
forth so even the aleksandar the
bhagirathi and other rivers they all get
their waters from
the ice melt and all that
in this overall region so if there is
plutonium lying around that could be a
very
dangerous thing
if the capsules break open for whatever
reason plutonium is
extraordinarily toxic
extremely toxic
it it first of all it can kill people
through its radiation secondly it can
kill people through heavy metal
poisoning and very small amounts of
plutonium are enough to kill people so
if
the plutonium is still lying around and
if it if the capsules break open then
they could leach into the ground water
yeah they could contaminate the rivers
the waters that flow into the electron
and the bhagirathi and other rivers that
feed the ganga that could be a disaster
for india because millions of people
live along the banks of the ganga
millions of people get their water from
the ganga
and so on it flows all the way down into
bangladesh is the padma river yeah
so that could be a massive massive
disaster so in case
the plutonium is still there
i think something needs to be done about
it i believe the indian government
every year periodically tests the
waters
or the snow or whatever in this region
for radiation that's what i i hear
i'm not sure so we don't know if the
proton is still lying around there or
maybe the indian government may have
retrieved it at some point in time these
things
probably will never be revealed to the
public for
the next few decades but yeah that is
the story that is as far as i know
so that's what happened in 1965 1966
the americans wanted to keep an eye on
the chinese and india was also
definitely
agreeable to that
and so this entire
episode happened
all right so that's the story about the
missing nuclear device
on the nanda devi
mountain in northern india
milan says was nepal ever a part of
bharat or has it always been an
independent kingdom
since ancient times
for those who don't know where nepal is
let's let's take a look at nepal
uh
so nepal is over here right north india
uh in the foot
the himalayas essentially the himalayan
region northern india that is now
the independent sovereign nation of
nepal so what is the story
well the nepalese said that they have
always
been independent since the since the
beginning that's what they say okay so
what does
the what do the facts of history tell us
right
so if you can see nepal is part of
jambodweep it's part of the indian
subcontinent it's very clear right it's
over here now what's the story so
nepal at various points in time has been
part
of
the kosala mahajanapada the panchal
mahajanapada the mahajanapada the kashi
mahajanapada and the virgika
mahajanapada which was a confirmation
confederation of various clans
led by the lecture we clan so these are
various mahajanapadas that nepal was at
various points of time
part of
kosal was one of the most powerful and
prosperous mahajanapadas of all time
right we know that yeah i hope you know
that panchal mala etc were also there so
nepal was the territory of nepal the
present-day territory of nepal was part
of this various mahajanapadas at various
points in time the mahajanapada era
begins right after the vedic era it most
likely lasted thousands of years
and the mahajanapada iran lasted until
about 500 or so bc
and then you had the various mughal
empires that came into place after that
so then you had various empires that
were based out of magadha the capital of
magadha was typically raj gear
raj
or
patliputra which is now called patna
right
so nepal the territory of nepal was
at various points in indian history part
of various empires based out of magda
for instance the nanda empire the fifth
century in the fourth century bc none
they done the empire was a massive
empire very strong powerful empire
short-lived but very powerful
the nanda empire was in power in india
when the greek warlord alexander
tried
to invade india disastrous in attempt to
invade india why did his soldiers rebel
against him because they knew the
military strength of the nanda empire
so when the nanda empire was in power in
india nepal the territory of nepal was
part of the territory of the nanda
empire then you had the mauryan empire
an even larger empire massive empire
nepal was part of the territory of
chandragupta maurya during the mauryan
impaired era and of course the even
larger territory of ashok ashok mori
ashoka the great also
encompassed incorporated nepal in it
right
so chandragupta in ashok
nepal was part of their empires then you
had the shong empire pushyam
185 bc right nepal was part of pushing
this empire
arrested the decline the imperial
decline of india at the hands of the
later mauryan kings and he
re-established political uh unity to a
large extent and stability in india so
nepal was part of the empire of pusha
mudrashunga very much so and then when
it comes to the question empire are you
even kidding me the kushan empire
it it touched the the banks of the
caspian c and the llc it also
incorporated parts of what is now called
xinjiang the tarim basin
river basin region and of course large
parts of northern india in western india
the capital of the kusan empire was it
had two capitals uh mathura and purush
or peshawar today partly putter was part
of it and nepal was very much part of
the kushan empire
now some very intelligent people will
say the questions were not indians
please take a hike kushan the kushans
were more indian than most indians you
think of
the koshan empire did more to promote
india's national interest civilizational
interest and to spread indian culture
worldwide than most indian empires you
know of so the questions were more
indian than most other indian empires
right then you had the gupta empire
right when did the gupta empire come to
power in the fourth century a.d until
about the middle of the fifth century
a.d the gupta empire they had some
magnificent brilliant rulers
chandragupta the first chandragupta ii
kumar gupta
so the
nepal region was very much part of the
gupta empire all right then you had the
karkota empire based out of sri lanka
kashmir another massively expansionist
and but short-lived empire parts of
nepal were part of the karkota empire as
well maybe whole of it then you had the
pala empire based out of the east of
india while parts of nepal were part of
the pala empire as well the pala empire
was a reasonably long-lived empire
around the mid middle of the 8th century
a.d
until the middle of the 12th century
so nepal was part of the pala empire as
well
so i hope i mean you can look all this
up yourself
don't ask me for sources do some
homework those of you who are gonna say
show me the evidence look it up i'm not
gonna spoon feed you all right so you
will be able to find all the
corroboration that you want of whatever
i have said in various history textbooks
if you will only take the trouble to
open open a textbook for yourself
and don't please don't rely on google
searches please don't do that do some
actual work
so nepal was always part of various
indian kingdoms and empires and it has
always been part of india the nepalese
people are no different from the indian
people same ethnicity same culture same
ancestry same everything same language
same culture same religion
and so on and so forth it's only in the
18th century that nepal emerged for the
first time as an independent entity
under uh
prithvi narayan shah who conquered the
navarre valley
and he forged this little imp this
little kingdom there and it is an
independent nation because of an
accident of history the british
deemed it uh worthwhile to allow nepal
to remain
nominally independent nominally outside
the british raj as a buffer state
because there was significant amount of
chinese interference in tibet at the
time
so they wanted a buffer
and that's why nepal remained nominally
independent but not truly independent
nepal has always been part of the indian
economy
nepal was always integrated with the
economy of the larger indian
subcontinent part of jambudweep right
so that's what it was
and
you may think that nepal was independent
as a kingdom but let me remind those of
you who don't
who don't realize this
that the incident in jillian wallabag
the massacre
just
revisit the chapter of history and find
out who was the who the soldiers were
firing bullets at unarmed civilians just
find out
at least fifty percent of the soldiers
who fired bullets at unarmed civilians
men women children were gorkas now i am
not blaming the nepalese people for what
happened
but i'm just pointing out the depal if
you think it was independent think again
yeah there is something called
independence in name and then there is
something called independence in fact
so these two things please understand
they are not the same
so anyway that is about the nepal nepal
has always been part of
india's civilization and culture
and in the future it will still remain
that
right
okay bobby says
it is said that the epic of gilgamesh is
one of the oldest surviving texts which
is dated to about 1800 bc the chins have
a book from confucius dated back to the
second century bc
the rigveda is older to my understanding
the surviving text was written on
perishable material
it was likely copied it's dated to about
1500 bc or so
so how can we tell the actual age by the
language by the material used or by a
special method of dating so there are
multiple ways of seeing of trying to
surmise what is the date of a certain
text or or a certain piece of literature
first of all you look for the oldest
hard evidence reduction evidence so i
think in the case of the epic of
gilgamesh it would be written on clay
tablets in uniform script so clay is
is is a hardy material especially baked
clay it can survive if you keep it in
the right in the right conditions for
thousands of years yeah
there are there's so many old clay
tablets that you find the the the treaty
between the mithani and the ha and the
hittites which which is the oldest
evidence of indian gods eric with the
gods
and so on that is cuneiform script on
clay tablets right so uh
so one of the ways
the first evidence you look for is the
hard evidence hard archaeological
evidence so i'm not sure what is the
oldest hard evidence of the rigveda
is the material is the text dated back
to 1500 bc maybe it is i'm not sure
maybe it is let's say it is so
in the old days
uh
texts were
written on birch bark
in northern india which is now gandhara
kashmir
right so gandhara is no longer part of
india as of today kashmir is obviously
part of india so in north india where
you had
birch birch trees and all that they
would write texts on birch bark they
would write texts on various other
perishable material
and uh and we had lots of texts in
universities and libraries which were
all destroyed so that's why we've kind
of kind of lost the actual heart
dividends of how old all of this is so
maybe i i'm not sure if if this this is
the correct date 1500 bc but let's say
it is
now it is believed
uh
the mainstream historians especially
coronal historians have been claiming
for the past 150 years or so that the
vedic age dates back to about 1500 bc
that is the all the chronology of the rn
invasion myth now how do we actually
date
the
approximate time period of the rig veda
so it's not gonna be possible to do it
based on hard evidence because the
oldest text that we have written
description will be dated to whatever it
is and maybe it's older than that so
one has to do a linguistic analysis to
understand
first of all what is the time period so
for instance the oldest hard evidence
written evidence of sanskrit that we
have
is found in the methane hittite region
which is present day anatolia let's put
that on the screen
let's go to the map
so this region here
northern syria
anatolia turkey this was the region
where three and a half thousand years
ago you had two major kingdoms here
one was the methane kingdom the other
was the hittite kingdom now the
interesting thing about both these
kingdoms is that they
spoke one spoke the hittite language one
spoke the hurian language which were
both local languages anatolian languages
but both of these kingdoms
had an aristocratic royal royal class
that spoke vedic sanskrit
so the royalty spoke sanskrit which
means that they were locals ruled by and
sanskrit speaking indian origin royalty
that's what it was and we know this for
a fact because we found the clay tablets
of their uh peace treaty in which the
gods indra mithra varuna etc are invoked
to witness the treaty and to bless the
treaty to make sure that it succeeds
and you also have a horse training
manual by the by a horse master the the
royal horse master of the nithani whose
name was kikuli so he wrote this horse
training manual
for training regular horses and making
them into war horses
a detailed manual in the hittite
language in the cuneiform script but the
problem he faced is that there were
certain terms that for which there was
no equivalent word in the hittite
language technical term scientific terms
so for those technical and scientific
terms he used sanskrit words because his
he clearly was proficient in sanskrit
so
so these are the oldest written
evidences of sanskrit that we have now
this has been known for a century or so
and uh linguists have done the
linguistic analysis of the kind of
sanskrit
that is
found in all these ancient inscriptions
and
it is
found that
the sanskrit
that is in evidence three and a half
thousand years ago in this region
is late vedic sanskrit so it has plenty
of words that are found in the veda and
the later vedas
but those words are extremely rare or
non-existent
in the rig veda so the sanskrit that we
have the vocabulary is very clearly late
vedic sanskrit
now these empires flourished the hittite
empire and the methane empire they
flourished
around 1500 bc
and they would the the
indians who migrated to this region
would have done so at least 500 years
before today so
before that time so they would have
reached this region around 2000 bc at
the latest maybe even before that
so that would tell us that around 2000
bc was the late vedic period
or maybe before that
and the rig vedic period must have been
maybe
a thousand years maybe 2000 years or
something like that before that we don't
know for sure so that is one way of
dating the approximate chronology
of the vedas that the rigveda would
definitely
come before 2000 bc
the other
evidence that we have is from the
rigveda itself the various mentions of
the river saraswati
it is mentioned as an actual river not
as a mythical mythical figurative liver
a river a literal actual physical
geographical river that's how it's
mentioned it's mentioned as a massive
river as the mother of floods is a
loudly roaring river
and glorious river and so on so forth
and now we know it existed i mean nobody
can deny it anymore it's it's there are
plenty of
research papers even in nature the most
prestigious uh
scientific general journal in which it
is now called the saraswati it is not
even called the
so it's now clear this river existed it
was the most massive river in india at
the time and it dried out around
1500 bc
it was last in its prime around 6000 bc
and it started declining slowly because
of
the the decline of the indian motion
monsoon
so it is clear that the rigveda would
have been written closer to 6000 bc when
the river was last in its prime and not
closer to 1500 bc so these are
approximate ways in which we can date
the vedas especially the rigveda because
the rigveda is essentially the starting
point of
the
essentially the starting point of the
vedic age and you could call it the
starting point of indian civilization
there are events that the rigveda
mentions and the puranas mentioned that
would have happened even before the
rigveda most likely but let's if we
consider consider the rig weather to be
the starting point of indian
civilization then it would most likely
have been written closer to 6000 bc
then to 1500 bc that's what we can
surmise so we have these various
indirect ways of gauging the approximate
time period of the vedas and the rig
weather but
we are still a work in progress as you
can see we still don't have a
very hard evidence of the exact time
period for sure so right now we have to
make do with approximate
chronological time periods
okay russia says
there was very cheeky of you to mention
demona it gave israel the samson option
i want to ask you if the vanu episode
was deliberate planned by the mossad to
make enemies of israel nervous or was it
plain stupidity on his part um
so i had mentioned something about
israel
a few episodes ago and i took a detour
on the map
at the mona so let's do it again in case
you're not aware of what this entire
matter is uh let's go to the map
so what is the mona
where is israel let's let's locate
israel we know where india is let's go
westwards westworth westwards
west of india you have a temporary
nation called pakistan then iran then
iraq then syria and west of syria and
jordan you have this small mid eastern
mediterranean nation of israeli
so what is the mona
let's go to the actual satellite imagery
where is dimona
where is the mona
[Music]
okay maybe it's not loading very quickly
so the mona is near beer shiva
here it is
in the desert
so let's take a closer look at demona
shall we
so this is the
town of the moon
now there is something interesting
nearby
where is the nearby thing let's see
maybe it's here
so what is this place
there are certain very characteristic
things that you see here
in one of these places
uh if you do some digging you will find
the tilting telltale signs
okay this is not the place this is a
fertilizer plant is it
all right here we are
the negev nuclear research center it
does research nuclear research
and as you can see here
it is kind of obfuscated and not very
clear maybe on purpose
maybe google is cooperating with israeli
government
but whatever you can see that there are
nuclear reactors at least one nuclear
reactor here
so this is the
and this is what gave israel the samsung
option which means the nuclear option
and this most likely happened in the
1960s 70s yeah that israel developed a
nuclear weapons capabilities
now what is the vanunu episode is the
question
there was this uh
technician israeli technician who worked
in the
negev nuclear
research
plant
his name
was
is
let's take a look at what this
gentleman looks like
morbe
all right let us put that on the screen
so this guy used to work that he was not
a scientist he was a technician of some
kind
and what this
guy did
is that he leaked in israel's nuclear
secrets
he uh
sold he took photographs surreptitiously
which is clearly i would say a breach of
security it is a lapse on the part of
the israeli government and the whoever
was in charge of security there
and then he sold these uh photographs
and the story
to
i think news of the world in the uk if
i'm not mistaken i may be wrong about
that but some publication in the uk
and uh
and then he was captured by the israelis
he spent some years in jail
in prison
i think he spent time globe trotting he
was in australia for some time he was in
various parts of europe and then he was
lured by the israelis through the good
old honey trap method
and he was captured he was brought back
to israel he spent a significant amount
of time in prison he converted to
christianity he started calling himself
david crossman or something some cross
man thing was there
and so on and now i think he lives in
israel he's not allowed to leave the
country
and yeah so that's the story of
mordechai vanunu
uh the israelis consider him to be a
traitor and uh he may think of himself
as
something else and so on so that's how
the world came to know about the fact
that the israelis had
nuclear capabilities and maybe
they have a significantly
non-trivial nuclear arsenal yeah
so the israelis have neither confirmed
nor denied the fact that the the
fact that they have nuclear weapons or
not but you can see that there is a
nuclear power plant in this place
the mona right
so what is the one episode is it
a deliberate plan by mossad to make
enemies of israel nervous or was it
plain stupidity on his part i'm not sure
maybe we will not know
so uh
one possibility i mean
uh yeah it's always good to let your
enemies know that you have certain
options yeah it's always good to do that
so in that case maybe it was deliberate
or maybe it was stupidity on his part or
maybe on the part of the israeli
government
so there are these are the various
options possibilities scenarios i don't
know for sure because hey
these are top secret matters
so maybe it was deliberate maybe it was
israel's way of letting its enemies know
that this is what we can do to you or
maybe it was just plain stupidity but i
think it has served israel well
that its enemies know that it has nukes
so maybe it was deliberate we don't know
maybe they used
somebody who was not very bright and
used in this manner manipulated him into
revealing secrets
which they wanted to be revealed that is
a possibility but we don't know for sure
we don't know
but that in short is the story
okay abhiram says how did the booming
economy of japan and its young
population in the 1950s 60s 70s 80s
turned into stagnation and older
population
right
so we know that japan was once a major
very rapidly growing economy booming
economy
i think in the
1980s i believe if i am not mistaken
japan had become the world's second
largest economy most likely by the time
the 1980s rolled into the picture
japan underwent this massive
rejuvenation of the nation after the
disaster of the second world war when it
was nuked twice
the whole nation was destroyed they
rebounded rapidly they went to work
they modernized very fast yes i think in
the 1960s 70s the the economy was
growing at 10 percent plus per year 12
plus per year very rapid growth yeah
so we know that japan is controlled by
the u.s the americans have more than 130
permanent
military bases on japanese soil the
constitution of japan has been written
by the us in 1945 not a single word has
been changed so the entire nation is
essentially a vasal state a puppet state
of the us
various japanese politicians have
revealed that no major decision can be
done by the japanese government without
the express approval of the u.s military
and the us government and so on
so this nation is fully controlled by
the u.s it is not a free nation it may
have elections it may have democracy
and the individuals may be free
but overall the nation is completely
controlled by the u.s understand that
now
so what happened
japan was booming the economy was
booming and suddenly something went
wrong so what happened is this in the
late 1970s early 1980s the japanese bank
the
the bank of japan the government
had kept interest rates very low
what does that do
when interest rates are low the people
and
the businesses
can borrow money it's it's good for
borrowing let's say you want to expand
your business
let's say you want to do more r d
research and development work you will
need money for that you need capital for
that if you can borrow money at low
interest rates it's good
let's say i want to borrow money and the
bank is giving me a 10 interest rate and
i want to borrow let's say 100 rupees
for five years
so after five years
i'm gonna have to give them 150 rupees
back because it's 10 interest per year
this is a very rough hypothetical
example but what if i'm getting the same
money at two percent interest rate
then instead of 150 i have to give them
110 after five years so if the interest
rates are low it it boosts the economy
it means there is more borrowing there
is more emphasis on research and
development and the economy grows so
during this time when the interest rate
was lowered the japanese economy grew
rapidly all the various japanese
technological firms like saudi and
whatnot they they did very well
there was a lot of emphasis on research
and development that's why the japanese
nation became the most technologically
advanced nation in the world right
now
in 1985 there was something called the
plaza accords
this was between the u.s
france germany uk and japan five nations
one is the us the other four are france
uk germany and japan
france
is a reasonably independent nation but
germany the uk and japan are proper
facal states of the us so these five
nations
decided
to manipulate international exchange
rates it was all done at the behest of
the americans
so what the outcome was of this
is that the u.s dollar depreciated in
value
and the japanese riyan the japanese
currency yen appreciated in value this
was manipulation of international
currency exchange rates
so when your currency becomes more
valuable more expensive
your exports decrease
your imports increase because your
population
which has
money
suddenly the money has more value so you
can buy more
so imports increase but your exports
decrease so that kind of flattens the
economy
so because of the plaza accords
japanese export suddenly slowed down and
imports started increasing
then
the the exchange rates were further
decreased yeah
so because of that the real estate
market in japan started booming
and real estate property became very
expensive and people started buying
property there was a big realistic
bubble and then for whatever reason the
bank of japan increased the interest
rates
what this did
was first of all there was a stagnation
of the economy the people
of japan who had bought all this
property expensive property suddenly
found themselves saddled with property
that is now lower in value
and now the in the loans that they'd
taken
they they had to pay more interest on
them now on the loans
because of this the entire consumer
behavior changed in japan and the
japanese people star stopped consuming
the cons they stopped spending money
and the the consumption
went down so there was deflation there
was stagnation of the economy and over
time this went on and on and even today
the japanese population the japanese
economy has not recovered from there the
japanese yen is now on very shaky ground
so this is not the entire story i'm just
giving you the very rough highlights
it is the actions of the japanese
government and the japanese the bank of
japan that caused this entire thing to
happen
they first kept the interest rates very
low
yeah and then there were the plaza
accords orchestrated by the americans
which manipulated the global exchange
rates it made the japanese currency more
valuable it made it appreciate
then there was the real estate bubble
engineered by the japanese bank the bank
of japan and then they suddenly
increased interest rates which totally
destroyed the economy so they called the
the
1990s the lost decade the decade in
which there was no growth in japan there
was stagnation almost no growth one
percent or two percent growth less than
two percent most likely yeah
maybe one point two percent growth and
uh
yeah so the economy shrunk
consumer behavior changed completely the
entire society became closed down
pessimistic
people stopped having children you know
everything became more expensive and you
can see the results of that today japan
has this rapidly aging population the
birth rates are way way down yeah
way below for replacement
and the economy is not doing well it's
still stagnating
so it all
originates in the actions of the
japanese government in the bank of japan
and all orchestrated by the americans in
the late 1970s mid 1980s late 1980s
that's where it all happened
and that's how the entire
nation went from a vibrant booming
economy into an economy that is beset
with with deflation and stagnation
that's where it is today that's what
happened
okay shazam says says please tell us
something about damascus steel
damascus steel
is a misnomer
it's a misnomer
the actual
steel
was indian steel
so
i don't know what its actual name was it
is
the the method of crea of of
manufacturing this of smelting this
steel is the crucible method it's called
crucible steel at various points in time
it has been called acidic steel or
whatever
um
let me show you what this particular
kind of steel looks like right
okay let's put that on the screen
so this is a very specific method of of
smelting steel in which you introduce
impurities carbon and all that various
things into the steel to give it a
certain
set of characteristics it's a very
strong steel if you uh do a microscopic
study of the kind of steel that you have
here you will find carbon nanotubes that
are introduced into it
in this process
it is known to have existed in india at
least since 500 bc
500 bc
india is the world's first completely
industrialized civilization and this is
a good example of that
so the oldest examples of this steel
manufacturing process the crucible steel
manufacturing process were discovered in
southern india tamil nadu and even sri
lanka around 500 bc and this steel was
exported to other parts of the world to
the middle east maybe to mesopotamia
maybe to egypt
the greek warlord alexander is supposed
to have been given a gift of
a certain amount of the steel because it
was the best steel in the world the
romans used to import this steel from
india
because they could not manufacture this
kind of steel and it was merchants in
damascus who used to import the steel
from india and when the europeans went
there they called it damascus steel it
is not damascus steel the merchants in
damascus used to import the steel from
india and then they would
man they would shape it into swords and
daggers and whatever else right so
that's why it's called damascus steel
but it's actually indian origin steel
it's got this incredibly beautiful
geometric pattern thing you know
so this is what damascus steel looks
like
and nowadays the manufacturing method is
reasonably well known
right
so it is not something that originated
in syria it's where the europeans first
found it
the europeans have this
habit of giving ridiculous names to
things
so when they first came into the eastern
asia region they found that the chinese
there were lots of chinese merchant
vessels
in a certain part of the world they
called it the south china sea
it's never been chinese it was always
the champa the champa samudra but they
called it the south china sea
when the british
took over parts of eastern india bengal
they called that part of the indonesian
the bay of bengal it's not the bay of
bengal it is the kalinga mahasagar
the british
named the western region the western
part of the indus indian ocean the
arabian sea
it's not the arabian sea it is the sea
of saurashtra
and so on and so forth they have this
horrible
tendency of giving inappropriate and
incorrect names to various things
whatever they see they give they give
their own
well names so damascus steel is not
damascus steel it is indian steel uh
as far as we know the oldest evidence of
this the manufacturing process
is
known to have existed in southern india
tamil nadu and sri lanka at least 500
around 500 bc maybe it must have been
much older than that we still don't know
when it actually originated so that's
how
old this manufacturing process is was
and it originates in india not in syria
or damascus all right
descendant of rigvedic clans says
who
is utsa the iceman what was his
connection with the north indian
population what is transitive script
okay okay okay okay three questions
let's take one
okay who was this guy who see the iceman
let's put him on the screen shall we
oozy the iceman okay this is i'm gonna
show you the image of a dead person in
case you don't like to see it switch off
all right so this is a person who died
about 5200 years ago
and he died in the european alps
in the region between between italy and
austria the alps in that region the
mountains
high up in the mountains
and he died and he froze to death i mean
he didn't freeze to death he died and
then his body froze and it was
discovered it was rediscovered in 1991
by i think hitchhikers or mountaineers
and they thought they had come across a
murder scene which actually was a murder
scene but it was 5200 years old so let
me show you what this gentleman looked
like yes it's a dead body
it's a mummified person i will not
enlarge the images in case it is
distressing for some people but this is
what it looks like this is a
reconstruction of the gentleman's face a
reasonably handsome person yes
maybe he needs a shave but yeah that's
what it is believed he looked like this
is a reconstruction of his appearance
and his visage
oatsie the iceman
now they make him look very european it
is known that he had
brown eyes
and
dark brown or black hair and his skin
was not exactly white it was light brown
he had a proper mediterranean appearance
and genetically he is close to the
people of the mediterranean region if
you look at the mediterranean region
southern italy
greece
lebanon etc
the skin color the skin tones you find
in these regions that's the kind of skin
tone that he had so it's not proper what
you would call the white race it's like
light brown trees
so that's
what this gentleman looked like so what
is this guy's story so they found the
body in 1991 if i'm not mistaken
frozen what what yeah this is what it
looked like
that's what he looked like when he was
found
um
as you can see that's how they found him
he was frozen stuck in the ice
then the body was extracted by various
researchers archaeologists whoever it
was it is now preserved some place i
don't know where where it is preserved
it is preserved at minus 23 degrees or
something and they take
good care to ensure that the body
doesn't degrade right and then they were
able to do ct scans and various other
tests of this gentleman and to figure
out how he died
so they found out that uh
he had some nice weapons uh he had a
flint or stone
knife and a copper axe a very good
quality copper axe he wore clothes that
were good for at least two three layers
of clothing good boots he had a fur cap
that was made up of of the fur of a bear
i think yeah
they were able to determine what kind of
food he did in his last meal there was
meat i believe of some kind
and uh
and then they found that they he had a
wound
on his hand
which came from grasping a blade which
somebody was trying to push at him so it
was a self-defense wound he tried to
grasp a blade
and it cut his his his palm to some
extent and the wound was healing which
means that he survived that attack or
that fight which he got into
and they also determined his cause the
cause of his death the cause of his
death was an arrow in his back
so yes it was a murder he was shot to
death he also had
i think
some kind of traumatic head injury
maybe hemorrhaging of the brain or
something which would indicate that
maybe he hit his head when he fell down
or maybe
he was hit on the head later on
something like that so it was not a very
uh peaceful death it was a violent death
he carried arrows
a bunch of arrows a bundle of arrows and
so on
so that's what we know about him this
entire thing his death happened about
about 5200 or so years before today
roughly
and it's one of the best preserved
ancient
naturally mummified bodies that exists
today
and there's still plenty of research
that's being done
on his uh body
so genetically he's believed to be
closely related to the people of the
mediterranean region the south
mediterranean also that sort of region i
am not sure what its connection is with
the north indian population and so on so
uh
not sure about that so that's what i can
tell you
okay mazar says is it true that the
indian subcontinent was first called
sindh later it became hindi because the
portions could not pronounce sa
let's go to the map to understand what
really happened
where is the map here's the map one
second let me let me zoom out of israel
okay
maps
come on
where's the map here it is
i'm not sure why it's showing me the
night side okay here where we are let's
put the actual map on
okay
so the question is is it true that the
indian sub current continent was first
called
sindh
no
the indian continent subcontinent was
called
jambudvipa
or aryawat
that's what
the indians
called it
now
where does this term thin comes from
come from
it comes from the river
sindhu
which the which is now called indus
in the english
language
the sindhu river
so it's the river that flows through
ancient mean underground present day
karachi
if i am not mistaken somewhere here
so the river
its its original name was sindhu
now you are right that the or our
persian cousins
or persian cousins could had a different
way of pronouncing the language
the old persian language was nothing but
a version a slightly distorted upper
branch version of sanskrit
the pronunciations were different so
instead of sir they would say ha
right
so instead of sindh they would say hinda
and the greeks and other foreigners who
came to india they came through persia
and when they would have conversed with
the persian friends of ours the persians
would have said yes yes hindu hindu or
their hind yeah eastwards so that's how
all the foreigners started calling india
hind that's how it happened it happened
because the persians called this region
the region of the sindhu river but they
called it the hindu region or the hindu
region and that's how the term india
came into the picture
which was a further corruption of hind
into india or whatever
so that is the story in brief how india
india came to be known as hind because
our persian cousins could not pronounce
pronounce sa even in western india there
are certain places
in gujarat rajasthan but even today
instead of sir they say
so there is some some some of that in
india as well
okay anurag says in the movie 300 it was
shown that xerxes had gargantuan
elephants and rhinos in his army
my question is is if the depiction was
true then where did he get where did he
manage to get those animals from us
they're not found in iran
so who was this uh gentleman called
xerxes first of all the movie is a
fictional depiction of something that
actually happened
it is a fictional depiction of the
battle of thermopylae
which happened in greece so xerxes was
one of the great
persian emperors of the haksha manish
dynasty the k minute dynasty his name
was not xerxes his name was
that's that's his name
he was the son of the rios the great
xerxes lived in the
fifth and
in the in the fifth century bc he ruled
iran persia in the fifth century bc let
me put that on the screen so that you
understand what what the region is
so this is the region of iran
he had a big empire and he expanded
westwards
he conquered anatolia and he fought the
greeks anatolia which is present-day
turkey
was historically greek territory the
greeks lived there the ancient city of
troy is found in anatolia in western
anatolia
so anatolia presented turkey was great
territory uh mr xerxes
emperor xerxes emperor claire conquered
anatolia and he ventured into greece
and he fought this great battle the
great the battle of thermopylae which
was a victory for the persians a defeat
for the greeks he was able to capture
athens the capital of greece and he
ordered this city to be destroyed and we
have discovered archaeological evidence
of the persian destruction of athens and
then the city was rebuilt obviously we
know that
so the question is in the movie
this this guy emperor crayola is
depicted as having had gargantuan
elephants and rhinos in his army
where did he get them from so first of
all the rhinoceros
is not an elephant you can tame
that is a massively dangerous and
incredibly powerful animal you cannot
tame it
and you certainly cannot use it for
warfare
so
that was what you what you call a
creative liberty in the movie the movie
makers took some creative liberties and
they portrayed this guy as having
rhinoceroses in his army he would not
ever have had rhinos it's possible that
he may have had elephants now obviously
we know that elephants don't live
elephants are not found in iran
so obviously he would have acquired them
from india see the persians
were descendants of indians lots of
close cultural ethnic
ties with india
india and persia were neighboring
civilizations
and i am sure india and porsha had
excellent relations the persians as far
as we know never ever tried to invade
india
during the entire time period of the
camera dynasty of the shamanish dynasty
so it's possible that india and turkey
india and porsha had excellent trade
relations cultural relations diplomatic
relations
marriage relations and what not
and therefore the persian emperor may
have acquired
elephants from india from whoever was
his counterpart as king or queen or
whatever in india at the time
so it's possible that the persians may
have had war elephants if they did have
them they would have acquired them from
india as far as rhinos are concerned not
possible rhinos are too violent too
dangerous and too unpredictable to be
tamed and you cannot use them for
warfare as far as i know to the best of
my knowledge all right so that's the
answer to this question
all right
next question pseudo podia says the thai
script is very much similar to the other
south indian scripts
however it includes sanskrit words can
you explain this
please understand the difference between
a script and a language a language
can include sanskrit words a script is
simply a writing system you can write
anything
in
any specific script
so for instance there is the latin
script which emerged out of italy
it was used to write latin the latin
language but after the romans conquered
most of europe that script was imposed
on all the local cultures and today you
write the english language
in the latin script
so the script is just a vehicle to carry
any language yep
so the thai script okay let's see what
the thai script looks like shall we
let's take a look at that let me put
that on the screen omniglot
omniglot
thai put that on the screen let's see
what the thai script or alphabet looks
like
come on here we are
the thai
uh language
this is what the script looks like as
you can see it looks kind of similar to
uh
various southern indian scripts even the
script of the oria language odi language
yes
this is what it looks like
all those vowels and consonants and all
that
so as you can see it's quite similar
to uh
various southern indian scripts what
about the burmese language let's take a
look at the burmese language
and the burmese script
and so on so forth it looks again
suspiciously
related to various southern indian
scripts let's take a look at the khmer
script of cambodia
what does the khmer script look like
here we are
once again as you can see it's quite
similar
to thai burmese and various ancient
or southern indian scripts let's take a
look at one more script from laos
the law script
which is spoken in laos in cambodia in
vietnam the language and this is the
script
kaka all that the same thing
once again very similar
all that stuff which we are very
familiar with if you have ever learned
any indian language
all of these scripts come out are
descended from the ancient pallava
script
which was written
in south india it was used to write
sanskrit various varieties of prakrit
including pali
and later it was exported to various
parts of south eastern india
south east asia
this is the pallava script
right
so there you are that's what it is so
and the pallava script itself is a
descendant of brahmi
so this
tells you this shows you the kind of
influence the enormous influence india
has had on southeast asia
on thailand on cambodia on laos on
vietnam on indonesia and all the way up
to the philippines then it goes way
beyond that
so uh
yeah so this is the thai language and
and that's why it is the way it is and
the thai script can even be used for
writing sanskrit
right so it's because of the insurance
industry it was first the
the kalinga empire and kingdom that
spread indian culture all the way across
southeast asia and then it was the
imperial cholas
who
who went a step further
and uh spread more indian culture and
possibly the pallava script in this
region right so that is the history
uh that explains
all of this
okay let's take a couple more questions
okay this is a question i've never had
before
hersh says please tell something about
gotham
one of the greatest rulers of india i
believe
and how sad vahanas pose challenges
to the belief that india has always been
a patriarchal society
okay the satvahanas i've never really
had a question on satwahanas so the
satwahana dynasty
was also known as the andhra dynasty
they ruled in
uh between the third century bc in the
first or second centuries bc yeah
in
southern and central india
it uh at its greatest extent it
incorporated parts of saurashtra gujarat
if you look at the size of the
greatest extent of the south mohana
empire it was roughly the size of
germany and spain put together big big
big its capital city was pratishthana
modern day python in maharashtra and
they were very good great patrons of
arts and culture and hinduism and
buddhism
and what not literature they built
supers and lots of things and
what does satwan mean the word saatvahan
is the prakrit form of the sanskrit term
and what is
subtitle of the sun which is driven by
seven horses so indirectly they are
implying that they belong to the surya
bunch the solar dynasty right
so uh the greatest king obviously was
gautami putra satakani
uh he was the son of queen
gotami balashri
he lived in the first or second century
a.d and he is said to have defeated lots
of people
the shakkas or the scithians the yamanas
the pahlavas and various other people
and his
extraordinary conquests are in
achievements are described in enormously
great detail very great detail in the
nashik inscription of his mother
now one of his greatest rivals was the
great mahat what was the was the western
satraps empire the great mahaksha tripas
of western india who ruled the region of
gujarat
rajasthan maharashtra parts of
maharashtra
parts of sindh and so on and so forth
so
it is believed possibly that gautami
putra satakani may have defeated the
great mahakshatrapa nahapana
and it this belief comes from the fact
from the known fact that many of naha
pana's coins are superimposed with uh
gautama putra shatta karni's
inscriptions
but that doesn't conclusively prove that
this actually happened maybe it is it is
possible or even likely that gautama put
the satakani may have lived uh one or
two generations after nahapana
was one of the
one of the greatest of rulers of western
india or possibly all of india possibly
even greater than gauthur
but gautam
himself was one of the great rulers of
india he had two two sons vashti putra
pulavami and vashishtriputra satakarni
um
and then after after him the empire
slowly declines his son married the
daughter of the mahaksha tribe
on the
and he still entered into conflicts with
rudra he was twice defeated by his
father-in-law
each time he lost territory but he was
spared because of the family
relationship and so on
and
eventually the the uh
empire declined and disintegrated over
time
uh the last ruler of the empire was
yajna sri sathya karni
who lived most likely in the second
century
but overall the greatest ruler of the
sat vahanas was gautama putra satakarani
who had
significant major achievements and was a
great patron of arts and culture and
religion literature who built
supers and things who did public works
so one of the great rulers for sure
so that's an interesting chapter of
industry that is typically not really
well known
and it's something that i speak about in
my course
all right let's talk about something
else
okay long question jack groshan singh
says i wonder how is the country able to
recognize its adversary and counter
attack if the nuclear-tipped ballistic
missile gets fired from the ocean for
the sea
using a submarine example
let's say india fires a nuke into china
from a nuclear submarine in the pacific
ocean
how is china going to figure out who did
this
because the submarine appears from
nowhere and after the after firing the
missile it disappears into nowhere
excellent question excellent question
so that is the point of having
submarines especially nuclear submarines
with long endurance they can say stay
like six months submerged without ever
coming up for air
so they can stay deep under the ocean
for months at a time
going around the oceans and then they
can fire a missile
from anywhere they want and then quietly
disappear
so how will
the nation that receives the missile
know where it came from and who is
responsible for the attack
that is the question that is a very good
question so it's like this
there is a whole
version of warfare happening right now
right now this very moment that we are
not aware of
submarine warfare
it is a cat and mouse game that's
happening as we speak right now there
are fleets of submarines in the pacific
ocean in the atlantic ocean in the
antarctic ocean in the northern ocean
arctic ocean in the indian ocean in the
bay of bengal in the sea of swarastra in
the persian gulf there are fleets of
submarines playing a cat and mouse game
right now
american submarines russian submarines
chinese submarines indian submarines
maybe even pakistan submarines they are
all shadowing each other
they are all trying to figure out who is
going where
and there are other
military assets involved in this ships
also monitor the movements of submarines
aircraft
are also equipped with with technology
that can detect
magnetic anomalies deep under the ocean
which is the signature of a submarine
right and so on
so
it is the job it is the professional
duty of every navy
to know exactly where the various
submarines of its enemies are at any
given point in time
and there are entire branches of the
navy dedicated to doing this
in a minute by minute basis
right
so you have satellites
firstly you have naval satellites that
keep a close eye on all the naval ports
and assets of your elimination let's say
india wants to know what the chinese are
doing with the submarines we know
more or less where the chinese submarine
bases are
so we keep an eye on these chinese
submarine bases through our satellites
which can do a day and night
surveillance
of course some of the submarine bases
are
underground and underwater and all that
so it's it's difficult but
that is the starting point
then once you know that a certain
submarine is out so you need to know
where the submarine bases are you need
to know exactly how many submarines your
enemy has
what are the classes what are the uh
ranges what are they what is the
endurance that each submarine has you
need to know this it's your job to do
this if you don't know it you're not
doing your job you're failing
then you need to find ways of tracking
the exact location of your enemy
submarines or on on a minute-by-minute
basis
so for that you have your own submarines
that will shadow the enemy submarine you
have your own uh naval vessels ships
merchant vessels disguised naval ships
these guys merchant visual vessels and
so many other things then you have
various choke points like the malacca
choke point
the strait of hormuz the strait of bab
al-mandeb the various 10 degree channel
other other channels in the andaman
islands through which these submarines
have to pass so you can keep an eye over
there
so it's a cat and mouse game that's
happening every single moment as we
speak
there are fleets of submarines of
various nations
that are shadowing each other and
keeping an eye on what the other is
doing there are chinese submarines that
are being shadowed by indian assets
there are american submarines that are
being shadowed by russian assets and it
is their job to know exactly what is
happening so that when one of them fires
a missile they will know immediately
and if they don't know they have
failed utterly
in their duty
so that's how it is okay so that's how
so it is not a foolproof thing sometimes
you may make a mistake and you will not
know where it comes from but if you are
a major power or if you are aspiring to
be a superpower it is your business to
be on top of this game
the submarine warfare game and you
should know exactly what is happening at
any given point in time vis-a-vis the
submarine assets of your enemies and
then you will know who did what
that's the answer
don garcin johan says
ebooks and pdfs have replaced paper
books to a great extent what's your take
on this is it something that needs to be
to happen
or is it just an increase in the already
high screen time of people well
technology is a double-edged sword on
the one hand it is making access to
books easier
you can now read books on your phone
yeah
and yeah e-books on your phone pdfs on
your phone so if you have a phone you
can read stuff anytime you want so it
makes
it easier to access books instead of
going to a library in borrowing a book
or purchasing a book which is expensive
you can actually get a lot of the stuff
online especially material that is now
copyright free or
whose copyright has expired or whatever
right and other things as well
so
on one hand it's great
on the other hand it's not good because
when you have the screen time when you
keep staring at screens there is this
blue eye the blue light
that goes into your eyes
and this blue light has the tendency of
keeping you awake
so it it delays the onset of the
melatonin hormone which is this signal
that you need to start sleeping so every
human being every person has a circadian
cycle
a sleep wake cycle
and it is something that is naturally
wired in your brain and this excessive
amount of blue light that you get from
various screens phones
laptops tablets whatever it messes up
the circulating cycle and that's what
causes various sleep disorders and
whatnot
so
in the old days
before sleeping people would spend half
an hour one hour reading a book
that's good
it slowly puts your brain to sleep if
it's a boring book or not yeah but if
you do the same thing with the screen
it's gonna prevent you from sleeping
it's gonna make you sleep less so yeah
it's it's bad so i
personally as you can see i prefer
physical books
i do use the pdfs from time to time
whenever required but i prefer to read
books in the physical form especially
before sleeping
so um
it's not something that needs to happen
in in some ways it's not good because
it's it's causing all these sleep issues
and all that
but it's it's just a sign of the times
we're in the 21st century and we are
facing these issues
i think physical books are still better
from my own perspective
but uh well
things change times times change and
people move on so that's where we are
lucky rahu online says hello abhijit
bhai
our ancient vedic culture observed
miraculous benefits of fast and
brahmacharya
you have also done it multiple many
times what's your experience so my
experience is
is with fasting i don't know the other
thing all right
yeah fasting is good
i have done multiple water fasts
extended water fasts i've even
documented that on on my other youtube
channel yeah
uh the first time i did an extended
extended fast was a 21 day water fast
no food only water for 21 days it was
fine yeah there was weakness and all
that yeah and there was this mental
cravings for food but overall it was
fine i lost obviously a lot of weight so
before you start a fast like that you
have to ensure that you put on some
extra weight before you want to start a
fast so that way your body will be able
to
burn out
all the excess weight that you've g that
you've put on and it will not cause any
health issues so the first fast i did
was a 21 day water fast the second fast
i did was a 23 day water fast
and uh
i think in december or something last
year
i did a third fast which was supposed to
be 21 day fast but i stopped at 14 days
so i have done that
i think that the human body is very
strong you can withstand
any kind of thing
and
i always ensure that i put on some
weight before i do an extended fast so
that way i'm safe and there is no health
issue and i always monitor my uh
vital signs blood pressure and heart
rate etc at the same time every day to
make sure that everything is is going
fine and so on my experience has been
great uh you lose weight you lose
strength you lose muscle mass which is
not nice but it's okay it's one of the
things that happens it's inevitable when
you go without food for an extended
period of time it gives you incredible
mental clarity and focus
and overall it's a very positive
experience yes it's kind of it's slow
motion torture because your mind craves
food
the body is doing fine but the mind
craves food and all so yeah that's been
my experience maybe i will do it again
in the future maybe once a year i can do
an extended fast 14 days 21 days
whatever depending on how i feel it's
not necessary but i think overall
fasting is beneficial
people who
fast periodically on a regular basis i
think they live longer um fasting
if you fast more than three or four days
go without food for three more than
three or four days then it triggers a
process called autophagy in the body
in which the body starts destroying all
the
damaged cells
dead cells
senescent cells
diseased cells pre-cancerous cells it
destroys them all and recycles the the
cellular materials so that's good for
the body
if if somebody has pre-cancerous cells
and they fast for let's say five days or
seven days it may end up destroying all
those pre-cancerous cells and so on so
forth so it has very good benefits it
makes your skin look good it overall
you know it
if you fast for more than four days i
believe you rebuild your immune system
from from scratch which is again a good
thing
so overall i mean it's it's always been
part of indian culture for thousands of
years fasting typically people would
fast on certain days of the week and
nowadays the west is copying it they
call it intermittent fasting and whatnot
yeah so
it's all being repackaged in different
ways by the west that's what happens so
overall i have a significant amount of
experience with fasting water fasting
going without food for extended period
periods of time zero calories for 21
days 23 days 14 days and it's worked
well for me i've overall felt very
positive there are obviously some side
effects you're going to lose weight
significant amounts of weight in a short
period of time you're going to lose
strength
and there are certain
symptoms that you experience that may
you may not enjoy overall but overall
it's a very positive thing so that's
been my experience
vis-a-vis
extended fasting i'm not sure about
brahmacharya that's not something that i
am experienced in
okay let's take some questions from the
live chat shall we
let's take some live chat questions
if there are any i will take two or
three questions before i'm done
okay uh this is by
sanathani i prefer physical books too
staring at the screen stay strains the
eyes no matter no wonder most of the
kids nowadays wear thick glasses i agree
i agree
kids are made to study all the time and
typically they are on a screen on a
laptop or a tablet or something and
close to your eyes
and yeah actually even i am nearsighted
when i go out i wear glasses
uh that's because i read too many books
as a kid and
maybe i kept them too close to my face
so
you get that even if you read books all
the time if you don't read them in the
proper way which i must have done but
yeah
yes i do prefer physical books
okay any other questions
let us see do we have any other
interesting questions that uh what is
lucid dreaming
what is lucid dreaming i believe it is
dreaming in which you participate
consciously
so you're not entirely asleep you're
kind of aware that of the fact that
you're dreaming of what you're
experiencing is not the real world it's
a dream and then you can kind of
possibly guide it in a certain direction
that sort of thing
so it's a it's a state in which you are
asleep you are dreaming but you are also
aware of the fact that you are dreaming
and you can take certain decisions and
and make the dream go in a certain
direction uh that's what they call lucid
dreaming i believe we've had this for
thousands of years it's called yoga
nidra or something
uh
yeah so that's not something i've ever
experienced or tried to experience but
it's something interesting something
interesting and yeah
you should try it if you can
it's something you learn
all right what do we have
[Laughter]
how to become a funny person i think the
best way to become a funny person is to
have a sense of humor
i know people who have no sense of humor
that is
well that's not funny so you want to be
funny
acquire a sense of humor develop a sense
of humor look for the funny things in
life yeah and that's how you become
funny i suppose i suppose i guess
all right let's take maybe one or two
more questions
uh
is there any other question
not sure
i can see all kinds of questions but
seven says best way to detox your body
you mean extended fasting water fasting
yes
certainly it's a very good way to detox
your body
who were the parthians they were an
indo-iranian people the descendants most
likely of the rig vedic prithu clan
who
were among who were on the losing side
of the battle of the ten kings there was
a confederation
that
fought this battle against the
against king sudas and they all lost and
one of the members of this confederation
was the prison clan
and most likely they are the ancestors
of the parthian peoples who are an
indo-iranian people who lived in the
western regions of india
perhaps
uh yeah the parthians yes
okay i guess we are done for today
we have again crossed two hours which is
always a good thing yeah so thank you
very much for all the questions and
let's keep on doing this please come up
with new questions interesting questions
you always have interesting questions
which i appreciate very much
so thank you very much we are done for
this week and i will see you in the next
episode
very soon until then take care
and keep going whatever you're doing all
the best